[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"1. This substance is mixed with water in an acidic soil called muskeg, which is commonly found in boreal forests. This substance is capable of storing up to 10 times more carbon dioxide than other ecosystems, leading to it being called the “world’s most efficient carbon sink.” It’s not coal, but the use of this substance as energy in Finland has raised global warming concerns. The genus Sphagnum makes up most of this substance, which dominates fens and quagmires. This substance consists of dead or decaying plant matter, primarily that of mosses. For 10 points, name this substance that accumulates in bogs. ","answer":"ANSWER: peat [or peat moss; accept bogland until “bogs” is read; prompt on organic matter; prompt on moss before “mosses”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"2. Merchants from this city smuggled relics out of Alexandria by covering them in pork to ward off Muslim authorities. This city’s mints produced a large silver coin called the grosso. This city’s Murano glassmakers were prohibited from traveling abroad by its ruling Council of Ten. Every Ascension Day, the ruler of this city dropped a ring into the water as part of a ceremony known as the “Marriage of the Sea.” The rulers of this “Most Serene Republic” resided in a palace overlooking St. Mark’s Square. For 10 points, leaders known as doges [“DOE-jiz”] ruled what maritime republic on the Adriatic Sea famous for its canals? ","answer":"ANSWER: Venice [or Venezia] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"3. The title character of this English-language play asks why some years have more eclipses than others, only to be told that he is “damned.” This play, which exists in “A” and “B” versions, includes a scene in which the phrase “homo, fuge” [“HO-mo FOO-gay”] appears on a man’s arm as he attempts to sign a contract. The title character of this play travels through time to play a prank on Pope Adrian and to visit Helen of Troy, of whom he asks “was this the face that launch’d a thousand ships?” Unlike Goethe’s adaptation of the same legend, this play ends with the title scholar being dragged to hell. For 10 points, name this Christopher Marlowe play about a man who sells his soul to Mephistopheles. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Tragical History of the Life and Death of Doctor Faustus [do not accept or prompt on Faust] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"4. One depiction of this figure may have been inspired by Agnolo Poliziano’s poem “La Giostra.” A wide canvas depicts this figure on the left as satyrs hold a lance and blow a conch into the ear of her sleeping lover. Simonetta Vespucci likely modeled as this figure for a painting in which a hora covers her with a cloak. The Three Graces stand to the left of this figure draped in red at the center of a painting set in an orange grove. A painting depicts Zephyr holding the nymph Chloris while he blows this figure to shore as she covers her nude body with her hair. For 10 points, Sandro Botticelli painted what Roman goddess standing atop a shell in a scene depicting her Birth? ","answer":"ANSWER: Venus [or Aphrodite] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"5. Some members of this phylum go through larval stages called planulae. An organism in this phylum can induce a life-threatening condition called Irukandji [“ee-roo-CON-jee”] syndrome. The presence of a box-shaped or cup-shaped body layout differentiates this phylum’s classes Cubozoa and Scyphozoa [“sigh-foh-ZOH-uh”]. In these organisms, the activation of a hair-like trigger causes the ejection of a venomous cell called a nematocyte. Animals in this phylum may alternate between two body morphologies: a sessile polyp phase and a motile medusa phase. For 10 points, name this aquatic phylum which includes sea anemones, corals, and jellyfish. ","answer":"ANSWER: cnidarians [or Cnidaria] [the “C” is silent] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"6. The founder of this party proposed a return to dual monarchy in the pamphlet The Resurrection of Hungary. This party elected the first female MP to the House of Commons, Constance Markievicz [“mar-kee-EV-itch”], and pursued the Armalite and ballot box strategy after the success of the Anti-H Block candidate Bobby Sands. Arthur Griffith formulated this party’s policy of abstentionism, which eventually led Fianna Fail [FEE-uh-nuh FOYL] to break away from this party under Eamon de Valera. This party’s military wing disarmed following Gerry Adam’s assent to the Good Friday Agreement, which ended the Troubles. For 10 points, name this Irish political party once linked with the Provisional IRA. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sinn Féin [“shin-FAYN”] [prompt on We Ourselves] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"7. Members of this religious sect call Sunday school “First Day School” because this sect uses a traditional calendar with numbered days and months. This sect’s core values are known as “testimonies” and can be memorized with the acronym SPICES. Books of Discipline are issued at this sect’s yearly meetings, some of which practice “waiting worship” instead of “programmed worship.” Early members of this movement did not swear oaths in courtrooms and used “thee” as a common pronoun. This sect’s founder George Fox encouraged individuals to sit in silence in order to hear the “inner light” of God. For 10 points, name this Christian sect that was followed by William Penn. ","answer":"ANSWER: Quakers [or the Religious Society of Friends; or the Friends Church] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"8. The reaction of one of these compounds with carbon monoxide and water was once used to produce acrylic acid. Aldehydes can be converted to these compounds via di-bromo-olefins in the Corey–Fuchs reaction. Treating these compounds with a strong base results in their namesake zipper reaction, which converts one of these compounds to their terminal type. These compounds contain at least one carbon that is sp [“ess pee”] hybridized. Lindlar’s catalyst converts these compounds to alkenes. Acetylene is the simplest one of these compounds. For 10 points, name these compounds that contain carbon-carbon triple bonds. ","answer":"ANSWER: alkynes "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"9. In one of this author’s plays, two men sing about a dog named Blue who “treed a possum in Noah’s Ark.” The protagonist of that play by this author recounts how his co-worker, Brownie, was fired for smuggling a watermelon under his coat. This author’s most famous play ends with a mentally handicapped man named Gabriel attempting to blow a trumpet. In that play by this author, the protagonist has an affair with Alberta and refuses to let his son Cory play football. This author’s play about the garbage truck driver Troy Maxson is the sixth work of his Pittsburgh Cycle. For 10 points, name this African-American playwright of Fences. ","answer":"ANSWER: August Wilson "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"0. This man is the dedicatee of Joyce Carol Oates’ “Where Are You Going, Where Have You Been?” An ode to “aretha / jukebox queen of hymn & him” opens his poetry collection Tarantula. This man, who included a photograph of his friend Allen Ginsberg on the back cover of Bringing It All Back Home, may have plagiarized the Moby Dick SparkNotes summary in a speech that he did not actually deliver; instead, he sent Patti Smith to perform “A Hard Rain’s a-Gonna Fall” on his behalf. At that ceremony, this man was recognized for creating “new poetic expressions within the great American song tradition” like “Blowin’ in the Wind.” For 10 points, name this folk musician who won the 2016 Nobel Prize in Literature. ","answer":"ANSWER: Bob Dylan [or Robert Zimmerman] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"1. It isn’t in Oregon, but this peninsula’s “Valley of the Giants” contains many gigantic cactuses. This peninsula was explored by Francisco de Ulloa [“day oo-YO-uh”], who disproved the long-held misconception that this peninsula was actually an island. Japanese immigrants to this peninsula’s city of Ensenada may have invented the fish taco. The mouth of the Colorado River is located on the northeastern base of this peninsula. Many obnoxious American college students visit this peninsula’s resort town of Cabo San Lucas. For 10 points, Tijuana is the largest city in what Mexican-controlled peninsula located to the south of California? ","answer":"ANSWER: Baja California [do not accept or prompt on “Alto California”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"2. A narrator created by this author is writing a manuscript on the Buddha, and becomes distressed when he is called a “bookworm” by a friend who sees him reading the Divine Comedy. In a novel by this author, Manolios acts as Christ in a passion play put on by his village. Translator Kimon Friar declared this author’s 33,333-verse follow-up to Homer’s Odyssey a “Modern Sequel.” This author’s best known character enthusiastically plays the santuri, seduces the aging hotel owner Madame Hortense, and is employed to work in the narrator’s lignite mine. For 10 points, name this modern Greek novelist of The Last Temptation of Christ and Zorba the Greek. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nikos Kazantzakis "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"3. A piece written in this genre uses an eight note motif that begins with the notes (READ SLOWLY): G, G-sharp, high F, E-natural. Stravinsky declared that that piece in this genre would be “contemporary forever.” Pieces nicknamed “Spring” and “Dissonance” are from a group of six pieces in this genre dedicated to Haydn. Pieces in this genre include one nicknamed “The Joke” and another that includes variations on a melody that would become the German national anthem. That set of pieces in this genre is called Erdödy. 68 Haydn pieces and Beethoven’s “Grosse Fuge” [“GROW-suh FYOUG”] were written in, for 10 points, what genre of pieces written for an ensemble of two violins, a viola, and a cello? ","answer":"ANSWER: string quartets [prompt on quartets] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"4. In this city, American diplomat John Allison was slapped after a squadron of planes attacking this city accidentally bombed the USS Panay. John Magee recorded footage during an event in this city that saw the German businessman John Rabe set up a “safety zone.” A contest to kill one hundred people with a sword took place in this city, which was once the site of the Porcelain Tower. This city was renamed Tianjing when it was the capital of the Heavenly Kingdom during the Taiping Rebellion. The first of the “unequal treaties” was signed in, for 10 points, what Chinese city subjected to a 1937 “Rape” by the Japanese army. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nanjing [or Nanking] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"5. According to the Purusha Sukta, this deity and Agni were created from Sukta’s mouth. This deity disguised himself as Gautama Maharishi to sleep with Gautama’s wife Ahalya; in response, Gautama cursed this deity to sprout a thousand vaginas over his body. This figure prevented Hanuman from eating the sun by striking him with a vajra. Most depictions of this deity show him holding a thunderbolt atop his white elephant steed, Airavata. This father of Arjuna used a wave of sea foam to defeat the demon Vritra. For 10 points, name this god of storms, the chief of the devas in Hindu mythology. ","answer":"ANSWER: Indra "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"6. This film’s cinematographer, F. A. Young, used a specially created telephoto lens to capture a wide shot of a black-robed horseman riding through a mirage. A famous “match cut” from this film connects a shot of the protagonist blowing out a match to a shot of a rising sun. Like The Seven Pillars of Wisdom, this film plays up the homoerotic element of the main character’s friendship with Sherif Ali. This David Lean film begins with the title character dying in a motorcycle crash, and ends with him liberating Damascus alongside Prince Faisal. For 10 points, what film stars Peter O’Toole as the British leader of the Arab Revolt? ","answer":"ANSWER: Lawrence of Arabia "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"7. A poem about this substance claims that it “levels life and death / and a thousand things obstinately hard to prove.” Du Fu named Li Bai as one of the “eight immortals” of this substance. Mo Yan wrote a satirical novel titled for the Republic of [this substance] as well as Red Sorghum, which is about a family that produces this substance. Eighteen bowls of this substance inspire Wu Song to slay a tiger in Water Margin. A poem about this substance describes how it is consumed by two friends “under the flowering trees” on the “Cloudy River of the sky.” For 10 points, name this alcoholic beverage, the subject of Li Bai’s “Drinking Alone by Moonlight.” ","answer":"ANSWER: wine [or sorghum wine; prompt on alcohol until it is read] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"8. This brother-in-law of Josephine Goldmark led the creation of the Savings Bank Insurance League in Massachusetts. This lawyer publicized the results of the Pujo Committee in Other People’s Money and How the Bankers Use It. With Samuel Warren, this pioneer of the Erie doctrine authored an article on “The Right to Privacy” and later condemned wiretapping in his dissent in Olmstead. This justice filed a namesake scientific brief on behalf of working women in Muller v. Oregon. A clash with Chaim Weizmann led this justice to resign from the Zionist Organization of America. For 10 points, name this first Jewish Supreme Court Justice. ","answer":"ANSWER: Louis Brandeis "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"9. This philosopher explained his use of the term “principle attribute” by reasoning that extension is the principle attribute of the body. Marin Mersenne accused this philosopher of making a circular argument in a “Second Set of Objections” to one of this man’s texts. This philosopher used the analogy of sorting rotten apples from fresh apples to illustrate the separation of false beliefs from true beliefs. A text by this philosopher discusses clear and distinct perceptions and states that, because the idea of perfection cannot come from a non-perfect being, God exists. For 10 points, name this author of Meditations on First Philosophy who stated “I think, therefore I am.” ","answer":"ANSWER: René Descartes "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"0. Scientists have proposed a “firewall” that destroys matter that enters these objects. The first gravitational waves were detected from a merger of two of these objects. The idea that these objects emit blackbody radiation due to mutually entangled particles was proposed by Stephen Hawking. An ergosphere surrounds the rotating type of these objects. These entities are characterized by mass, charge, and angular momentum according to the no-hair theorem. The Schwarzschild radius defines the event horizon of these objects, which contain a gravitational singularity. For 10 points, name these objects that have such a high gravitational pull that not even light can escape them. ","answer":"ANSWER: black holes Tiebreaker. The deformation of regions named for this substance can be described by the Mogi model. This substance may undergo a form of “differentiation” that can be caused by contamination from wall rocks or bulk assimilation. Batholiths, dikes, and sills can be formed when this substance solidifies. Bowen's reaction series describes this substance’s fractional crystallization, which produces minerals such as olivine and pyroxene. Gabbro, granite, and other intrusive rocks can be formed in this substance’s namesake \"chambers\". For 10 points, name this type of molten rock that has not reached the surface of the earth and is contrasted with lava. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this poem from Lewis Carroll’s Through the Looking Glass. It warns the reader to “beware the Jubjub bird” and “shun the frumious Bandersnatch” in addition to the fearsome title creature. ","answer":"ANSWER: “Jabberwocky” "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This protagonist of Through the Looking Glass encounters the Cheshire Cat and the Mad Hatter in a Carroll book about her Adventures in Wonderland. ","answer":"ANSWER: Alice [or Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This other poem from Through the Looking Glass describes ten crew members, including a Butcher who can only kill beavers and an actual Beaver, on their search for the title Boojum. ","answer":"ANSWER: “The Hunting of the Snark (An Agony in 8 Fits)” "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this uprising of Russian soldiers who swore loyalty to the Grand Duke Constantine, who had removed himself from succession. The Northern Society rallied officers in Senate Square in this event’s namesake month. ","answer":"ANSWER: Decembrist Revolt "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Constantin was the elder brother of a Tsar of this name. The second Russian tsar of this name was executed by Bolsheviks in 1918 on the orders of Vladimir Lenin. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nicholas [or Nicholas I; or Nicholas II] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This son of Nicholas I granted the Decembrists amnesty upon taking the throne. This tsar planned to implement Count Loris-Melikov’s reforms but was assassinated by People’s Will before he could put them into effect. ","answer":"ANSWER: Alexander II [prompt on partial answer] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this strong diprotic acid, also known as oil of vitriol. ","answer":"ANSWER: sulfuric acid [or H2SO4 ] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The Takai reaction uses a reactant containing this metal’s chloride to convert ketones to alkenes. The reagent PCC consists of a pyridinium atom and an anion [“ann-EYE-on”] with this transition metal at its center. ","answer":"ANSWER: chromium [or Cr] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Sulfuric acid, chromium trioxide, and acetone make up the Jones reagent, which acts on the primary and secondary type of these compounds. These compounds contain a hydroxyl functional group. ","answer":"ANSWER: alcohols "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this instrument. This instrument plays the melody after the bassoon in Ravel’s orchestration of “The Old Castle” from Modest Mussorgsky’s Pictures at an Exhibition. ","answer":"ANSWER: saxophone [or alto saxophone; or tenor saxophone; or sax] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The alto saxophone plays a slow melodic solo in the first of this composer’s Symphonic Dances. This composer wrote a tone poem based on an Arnold Böcklin painting titled Isle of the Dead. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sergei (Vasilyevich) Rachmaninoff "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Both Mussorgsky and Rachmaninoff were composers from this country. This country is the setting of Mussorgsky’s opera Boris Godunov. ","answer":"ANSWER: Russia [or the Russian Empire] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this Chinese philosopher who wrote a text in which he asks a skull “how do you know it’s bad to be dead?” In that text, this man defended a supposedly useless tree by saying one could admire it or nap under it. ","answer":"ANSWER: Zhuangzi [“ZHUANG-zuh”] [or Zhuang Zhou; or Chuang Tzu] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The Zhuangzi is an important text in this Chinese religion that emphasizes wu-wei, or “non-action.” This religion is typically represented by the yin-yang symbol. ","answer":"ANSWER: Taoism [or Daoism] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Early Taoism was strongly influenced by this other Chinese text, whose 64 hexagrams can be used to perform divination. ","answer":"ANSWER: I Ching [or Classic of Changes; or Book of Changes] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this essay that asserts that “existence precedes essence.” This essay defines “abandonment” and “anguish,” and expresses man’s individual responsibilities through the phrase “in fashioning myself, I fashion man.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Existentialism is a Humanism [or L’existentialisme est un humanisme] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This French philosopher introduced his idea that “existence precedes essence” in Existentialism is a Humanism. The concepts of “being-for-itself” and “being-in-itself” are discussed in his book Being and Nothingness. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jean-Paul (Charles Aymard) Sartre "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This Sartre concept refers to when individuals deny their innate freedom and accept inauthentic values as a result. To illustrate this concept, Sartre used the examples of a woman on a first date and a waiter in a cafe. ","answer":"ANSWER: bad faith [or mauvaise foi] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this curve that demonstrates the effects of tradeoffs. Introductory economics classes often use this curve to plot the relationship between guns and butter. ","answer":"ANSWER: production possibility frontier [or production possibility curve; or PPC; or PPF] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Points located along the PPF are considered to have the productive form of this condition. Vilfredo Pareto generalized it to a state in which any reallocation of goods will make an individual worse off. ","answer":"ANSWER: efficiency [or productive efficiency; or Pareto efficiency; or Pareto optimality; accept word forms such as efficient] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Two answers required. The Heckscher-Ohlin model uses PPFs to determine the intensity of goods relative to these two quantities, which determines what countries export and import. ","answer":"ANSWER: labor and capital [accept in either order] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this diagram in which each number is equal to the sum of the two numbers above it. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pascal’s triangle [prompt on partial answer] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The numbers found in Pascal's triangle are also called these numbers, which are the coefficients of a two-term polynomial raised to an exponent n. ","answer":"ANSWER: binomial coefficients [or binomial numbers] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The sum of the nth binomial coefficients, or equivalently the sum of the nth row of Pascal's triangle, is this function of n. ","answer":"ANSWER: 2 to the n [or 2 to the power of n] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this proponent of “brinkmanship” and “massive retaliation” who served as Secretary of State under Eisenhower. His younger brother Allen was CIA Director in the 1950s and early 1960s. ","answer":"ANSWER: John Foster Dulles "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The Dulles brothers supported Operation PBSUCCESS, a CIA-led plot to overthrow this democratically elected president of Guatemala. His land reform policies antagonized the United Fruit Company, which owned the majority of Guatemala’s banana plantations. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jacobo Árbenz Guzman "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The Dulles brothers also orchestrated a 1953 coup in this country, which strengthened Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi’s grip on this country’s throne. In 1979, an angry mob captured the US embassy in this country’s capital city of Tehran. ","answer":"ANSWER: Iran "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this type of animal. The final section of a 1984 novel is titled for the dying “Smile” of a female one of these animals that Tereza gives the masculine name “Karenin.” ","answer":"ANSWER: dogs "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Both of the aforementioned novels were written in this European language, which was also used by playwright and president Václav Havel [“VAWT-slahv HUH-VELL”]. Ludvik Vaculik [“VAWT-soo-leek”] used this language to write the “Two Thousand Words” manifesto during the Prague Spring. ","answer":"ANSWER: Czech "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Tomas, Tereza, and their puppy Karenin escape the Soviet invasion of Prague in this Czech author’s novel The Unbearable Lightness of Being. ","answer":"ANSWER: Milan Kundera "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this 1957 album by John Coltrane, featuring trumpeter Lee Morgan and bassist Paul Chambers, which includes the tracks “Moment’s Notice” and “Lazy Bird.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Blue Train "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This trumpeter pioneered modal jazz on an album featuring the songs “Blues in Green” and “All Blues,” Kind of Blue. ","answer":"ANSWER: Miles Davis "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Hard bop saxophonist Joe Henderson premiered a Kenny Dorham composition titled for the “blue” form of this genre. This Brazilian jazz genre, which is distinct from samba music, was popularized in the United States by Stan Getz and Astrud Gilberto’s recording of “The Girl from Ipanema.” ","answer":"ANSWER: bossa nova [prompt on “Blue Bossa”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this property. The relativistic interaction of this property with a particle’s orbit contributes to atomic fine structure. ","answer":"ANSWER: spin [prompt on intrinsic angular momentum; do not accept or prompt on “angular momentum” alone] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The existence of spin was confirmed in this experiment named for two German scientists, who fired a beam of silver atoms into an inhomogeneous magnetic field. ","answer":"ANSWER: Stern–Gerlach experiment "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This scientist lends his name to a set of commutative spin matrices. He also names an exclusion principle that states that two or more fermions cannot occupy the same quantum state in a system. ","answer":"ANSWER: Wolfgang Pauli "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this friar who preached against luxury and corruption and orchestrated the Bonfire of the Vanities. ","answer":"ANSWER: Girolamo Savonarola "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Savonarola preached in this Tuscan city, where he became the de facto ruler after its ruling Medici family was expelled. ","answer":"ANSWER: Florence [or Firenze] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This pope unsuccessfully tried to silence Savonarola with a cardinalate, then had him excommunicated. According to legend, this pope invited prostitutes to the Vatican for a debauched “Banquet of the Chestnuts.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Pope Alexander VI [or Rodrigo Borgia; prompt on Borgia or Alexander alone] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this author of The Spy Who Came in from the Cold. George Smiley works for a British intelligence group known as the Circus in his Tinker Tailor Soldier Spy. ","answer":"ANSWER: John le Carré [accept David John Moore Cromwell] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"6. ","answer":"ANSWER: Our Man in Havana "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This fictional British spy appears in several novels by Ian Fleming, including Casino Royale and From Russia with Love. ","answer":"ANSWER: James Bond [accept either underlined name; or 007 [“double-oh seven”]] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this country that implemented mandatory capital punishment for drug offenses under its longtime ruler Lee Kuan Yew. ","answer":"ANSWER: Singapore "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Like Singapore, this other Southeast Asian country uses the death penalty for most drug smuggling cases. Its capital city is Jakarta. ","answer":"ANSWER: Indonesia "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] In 2015, Australia cut its foreign aid to Indonesia after this Indonesian president refused to pardon two Australian citizens accused of drug smuggling. ","answer":"ANSWER: Joko Widodo [or Jokowi] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Identify this rustic god associated with beekeeping and honey. This god is the son of Apollo and Cyrene. ","answer":"ANSWER: Aristaeus "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] After Aristaeus caused the death of Eurydice, this son of Apollo and Calliope went to the underworld in a failed journey to retrieve her. This man was torn to pieces by Maenads while playing songs on his lyre. ","answer":"ANSWER: Orpheus "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This son of Apollo and Coronis was a god of medicine who brought back Hippolytus from the dead. People would sleep in temples of this god in order to be healed. ","answer":"ANSWER: Asclepius "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this general who allied with Cassander and Lysimachus to defeat Antigonus the One-Eyed at the Battle of Ipsus. This member of the Diadochi bore the epithet “Nicator” and founded the city of Antioch. ","answer":"ANSWER: Seleucus I Nicator "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"2. ","answer":"ANSWER: Alexander the Great [or Alexander III of Macedon; prompt on Alexander] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Seleucus married his daughter to this Indian emperor, who supplied the elephants that Seleucus deployed at the Battle of Ipsus. This grandfather of Ashoka founded the Mauryan dynasty. ","answer":"ANSWER: Chandragupta Maurya "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Friedrich Wöhler’s accidental synthesis of what compound from inorganic substances helped refute the idea of vitalism? ","answer":"ANSWER: urea [or carbamide; do not accept or prompt on uric acid or urine] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] The fumarate produced during the urea cycle is also an intermediate in this other cycle that occurs in the mitochondrial matrix. This cycle follows glycolysis during cellular respiration. ","answer":"ANSWER: Krebs cycle [or citric acid cycle; or CAC; or tricarboxylic acid cycle; or TCA] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] At one step of the urea cycle, CPS1 catalyzes a reaction between this ion, ammonia, and two molecules of ATP. Levels of this ion are abnormally high during respiratory alkalosis. ","answer":"ANSWER: bicarbonate ion [or HCO3 - ] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this title character of a 1936 short story who is accidentally shot by his wife, Margot, during a safari in Africa. ","answer":"ANSWER: Francis Macomber [accept either underlined part; or “The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] This author of “The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber” included his recurring character Nick Adams in stories like “Big Two-Hearted River” and “Indian Camp.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Ernest Hemingway "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] In this Hemingway novella, the elderly fisherman Santiago muses about Joe DiMaggio as he attempts to catch a marlin. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Old Man and the Sea "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name this sculptor who depicted a naked couple dancing in The Waltz. Her sculpture The Mature Age is often interpreted as an allegory for her relationship with her lover, who abandoned her to live with his mistress Rose Beuret. ","answer":"ANSWER: Camille Claudel "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Claudel was a collaborator and lover of this French sculptor, who signed his name on some of Claudel’s works. He sculpted The Thinker for his never-completed project The Gates of Hell. ","answer":"ANSWER: François Auguste René Rodin "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Claudel may have assisted in the creation of this Rodin sculpture, which depicts Paolo and Francesca from Dante’s Inferno. It was removed from Gates of Hell because of its controversial eroticism. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Kiss [or Le Baiser] Tiebreaker. Two answers required. In 2002, these two countries engaged in a brief bloodless “war” over control of the Perejil [“peh-ruh-HEEL”] Island. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Name these two countries that dispute control over the enclaves Ceuta and Melilla [meh-LEE-yah”]. ","answer":"ANSWER: Spain and Morocco "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"[10] Although Spain refuses to cede control of Ceuta [“see-OOT-ah”] and Melilla back to Morocco, it has frequently protested Britain’s ownership of this strategically important strait. It connects the Atlantic Ocean to the Mediterranean Sea. ","answer":"ANSWER: Strait of Gibraltar "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"L","question":"7. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Rif [or the Rif War]"}]
